Hello everyone and
welcome back to English
Pod, my name is Marco
and my name is Catherine
and we've got a great lesson for
you today, what level is this, Marco?
This is an elementary
lesson and we're going
to be touching one
of these medical topics.
Today we're going to
talk about chicken pox.
Oh gosh, I hated the
chicken pox, they're
horrible and they itch
and you can't do anything
about it and your
parents say don't scratch.
So chicken pox is a
illness that you get
usually as a child and
what happens is you start
getting these little red dots all over
your body, like little mosquito bites.
Exactly and they come
all over your body,
your arms, legs, and
face and you can only get
this disease once, unless maybe
you didn't really get it too seriously.
So most people get
this one there, children.
Exactly and what makes
you very uncomfortable
when you get chicken
pox, as you said, it's
these little red dots,
they itch just like
mosquito bites, but
you can't scratch because
if you do, then you get
your skin gets marked, right?
You have like stains ever for like scars.
So it's best not to scratch and that's
what we're going to talk about today.
Somebody has the chicken pox.
So let's listen to our dialogue for the
first time and then we'll be right back.
What's wrong with you?
Why are you scratching so much?
I feel good, she I can't stand anymore.
I think I may be coming
down with something.
I feel lightheaded and weak.
Let me have a look.
Whoa, get away from me.
What's wrong?
I think you have chicken pox.
You're contagious.
Get away, don't bring it on me.
Maybe it's just a rash or an allergy.
We can't be sure and twice the adductor.
Well, in the meantime, you're a biohazard.
I didn't get it when I
was a kid and I've heard
that you can even die
if you get it as an adult.
Are you serious?
You always blow things out of proportion.
In any case, I think I'll
go take an oatmeal bath.
Ew.
All right, we're back, so I think
this kid does have the chicken pox.
Definitely.
And well, he's got a funny solution for it,
but before we get there, we've got a lot
of great medical words,
such as basic body
words, for you in today's
language, take away.
Language takeaway.
All right, so let's start
with our first word.
He mentioned that he felt itchy.
I feel itchy.
Itchy.
So, okay, this is often
confused, even among
children who are native
speakers of English,
there are two words
to itch and to scratch.
But this person is itchy, so it means
that your skin, you want to scratch it.
It's maybe uncomfortable,
like a mosquito bite is itchy.
Okay.
So itchy would be the adjective,
right, to the noun in itch.
So if you have an itch,
you feel itchy, right?
Exactly.
And that's when you scratch,
all right, so he feels itchy.
And he also felt a little bit light-headed.
Okay, so you know the word
head, you know the word light.
So here we have a person
who feels light-headed,
it means that you
kind of feel a little
bit strange and your head is a little bit,
well, what's a good word to describe it?
Like, dizzy.
Yeah, almost dizzy or faint.
Right.
So you usually feel a
little bit weak, you don't
really feel very well,
your head is light-headed.
The complete opposite of
having a headache, right?
Exactly.
Okay.
And well, then the girl got scared and
she said, get away, you are contagious.
Oh gosh, now this is a dangerous one.
Someone who is contagious can
pass their illness to someone else.
So for example, the flu is very contagious
and if I have the flu, Marco doesn't want
me to, you know, come
over and touch all this
stuff and sneeze and
cough into his food.
Right.
Exactly.
So that's contagious.
It's an adjective and that means that you
easily pass your illness to another person.
Exactly.
So why don't we take
a look at a couple of
different examples using
this word, contagious?
Example one.
Don't get near me, chicken
pox are very contagious.
Example two.
The sickness that is going
around the office is very contagious.
Example three.
Each one in one flu is very contagious.
All right, so you want
to avoid contagious
people, but you might also want to
avoid people who have this next word.
It's called a rash.
A rash.
Exactly.
So why do you want to
avoid people who have a rash?
Well, they might have
a contagious rash, who
knows, but you can get a rash
for a number of different reasons.
A rash is just basically
a part of your skin
that becomes irritated or uncomfortable
and sometimes it turns red or pink.
Exactly.
So as you said, it happens
for different reasons.
Sometimes you maybe
have bad seafood and your
skin and you start to have
rash is all over your body.
Other times you can
touch some plants that
are dangerous like
poison ivy or poison oak.
And then you get a big rash.
And our last word for
today is a little bit dramatic.
She called him a biohazard.
Biohazard.
Well, let's take a take a look
at these words individually.
The first word bio comes
from the word biology.
So that's something that is alive,
an animal, a plant, or a person.
And hazard is something that is dangerous.
So biohazard is a, well, something
that's alive that's dangerous.
Right.
Or that's dangerous
towards a living person, right?
Or organism.
For example, you don't want to be
near an area that has a lot of radiation.
It's a biohazard.
And exactly, or some
of these diseases like
Ebola virus, these are very
dangerous towards living things.
And so biohazard is the name for you.
Exactly.
And usually it's,
there's a symbol, a very
clear symbol that kind of
looks like a triangle, it's red.
And even in movies, it's appeared, right?
I think in that movie.
Yellow.
It's red or yellow.
Yes.
And that's, mm-hmm.
All right.
So biohazard.
I think we've taken a
look at a lot of words.
So why don't we listen
to this dialogue again?
Let's slow it down a little bit.
See if we can understand a little bit more.
What's wrong with you?
Why are you scratching so much?
I feel itchy.
I can't stand it anymore.
I think I may be coming
down with something.
I feel lightheaded in a week.
Let me have a look.
Whoa, get away from me.
What's wrong?
I think you have the chicken pox.
Your contagious.
Get away.
Don't breathe on me.
Maybe it's still the rash or an allergy.
We can't be sure until I see a doctor.
Well, in the meantime, you are a biohazard.
I didn't get it when I
was a kid and I've heard
that you can even die
if you get it as an adult.
Are you serious?
You always blow things out of proportion.
In any case, I think I'll
go take an oatmeal bath.
Ew.
All right, we're back.
So now why don't we
take a look at fluency
builder and start taking
a look at all these phrases.
Fluency builder.
Well, the first one is something that we
often say when we're starting to feel ill.
This phrase is coming
down with, so I could say,
I think I'm coming down
with a cold, for example.
So basically you say
I'm coming down with
something, so a cold or I think
I'm coming down with the flu.
So you're saying that
I think I'm getting ill?
Exactly.
It means I'm just
starting to feel sick, and
so you could say I've
had a cold for a week.
You wouldn't use the phrase I'm
coming down with in this situation.
You'd only use it when
you're starting to feel sick.
Very good.
You could ask your boss, eh, I
think I'm coming down with the flu.
Can I go home early?
Right.
And I think this is a very useful phrase.
It's very natural to say.
So why don't we listen to
a couple of other examples?
Example one.
Honey, will you take my temperature?
I think I'm coming down with something.
Example two.
You must be coming down with a cold.
Whole three.
Tommy came down with the flu.
All right.
So coming down with coming down with the
flu, coming down with the cough, et cetera.
All right.
What's our next phrase?
Well, this one's great.
It's a filler phrase.
So in the meantime, in
the meantime, so I could
say, all right, I'm going
to go cook dinner.
In the meantime, Marco,
can you please clear the table?
OK, so while you are cooking
dinner, I am doing something else.
I'm cleaning the table.
So two things happening at the same time.
In the meantime, very good.
So it's a filler, you say.
Because usually it follows another phrase.
So I'm going to be doing
this report for a while.
In the meantime, can you just
wait here on the sofa, please?
OK, very good.
So in the meantime, so you're connecting
two different actions, two different ideas.
Exactly.
Very good.
In the meantime.
And what about our last phrase?
All right, there are some
people who really like to do this.
And I might be one of them.
It's called it to blow
things out of proportion.
All right, and you're going to hear this
phrase a lot with native English speakers.
And so to blow things
out of proportion, well,
pretty much means
that you're exaggerating
or you're making a really big deal
out of something that's not very serious.
So for example, if you
come over to my house
and you break a glass
and I start freaking
out and yelling at you
because you broke my glass, I
say, Marco, you're blowing
things out of proportion.
I'll just buy you a new one.
It's not that serious.
All right, so don't exaggerate, right?
Right.
So oftentimes, you feel
like this with siblings,
spouses, or bosses
who react very seriously.
So you can say, hey, stop, stop yelling.
Like you're blowing
things out of proportion.
This is not a really big deal.
Exactly.
All right.
So blowing things out of
proportion, let's not do that.
But let's listen to our dialogue for
the last time and then we'll be back.
What's wrong with you?
Why are you scratching so much?
I feel, gee, I can't stare anymore.
I think I may be coming
down with something.
I feel lightheaded and weak.
Let me have a look.
Whoa, get away from me.
What's wrong?
I think you have chicken pox.
You're contagious.
Get away.
Don't bring it on me.
Maybe it's just a rash or an allergy.
We can't be sure and ties to your doctor.
Well, in the meantime, you're a biohazard.
I didn't get it when I
was a kid and I've heard
that you could even die
if you get it as an adult.
Are you serious?
You always blow things out of proportion.
In any case, I think I'll
go take an oatmeal bath.
Ew.
All right, so Catherine, have
you ever had the chicken pox?
I did.
I have very, very clear
memories of when I
was a child and I had
the chicken pox because
I believe it was
Thanksgiving and I was about
four, four or five years old and I couldn't,
I didn't have an appetite so I was not
hungry and all I could
do was itch and drink
and so I still have little
scars like you mentioned from
where I couldn't stop myself
from scratching my little marks.
Right.
Well, why does the little boy say that
he's going to go take a oatmeal bath?
Oatmeal bath?
Okay.
Well, this is one of the
home remedies, one of
the home cures for
the itchiness, all right?
So it doesn't make your
chicken pox go away
but it does make your skin feel better
because it's very calming and smooth.
So you can have some
creams or some lotions
but other people like
to take an oatmeal bath.
Right.
So then you're not itching anymore.
Right, but it's gross because
you're sitting in oatmeal.
It is kind of gross.
Have you had the chicken pox?
I did.
I didn't know but because I couldn't remember
so actually my brother had it recently
so I was afraid that
I didn't get it but
called my mom she
said I got it so I'm good.
You're safe.
Yeah, so that's the thing, right?
You can only get it once.
So once you get it, you
don't have a problem.
Well, we're curious to know, have you had
the chicken pox and if you did, was it, was
it really itchy or were you a
lucky one and it wasn't so bad?
So let us know in our
website EnglishPod.com, right?
And if you ever had any
other common childhood
illnesses like the mumps or the measles,
right, you can also tell us about that.
So we'll see you guys there
and until next time, bye, everyone.
[MUSIC]